Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
- Maps/Plans
  - ---. These Severall parcells of Land were surveid for Mr Wm. Sherwood ye 15th of August 1686 pr me Jon Soane., 923
    Size: 33 x 42 cm. Scale: 7 cm. = 18 chains Apparently shows two areas of the Jamestown peninsula. One area appears to extend south from the isthmus and is bounded by the James River, Sandy Bay, Back Creek, marsh, Mr Richard James's Land, and what may be a creek or another strip of marshland. Within this area there are two parcels, one of eight acres and one of 20 acres. A faint line labeled Roades extends across the area from the isthmus to the southeast. Block House Hill is indicated near the isthmus. The second area on the sheet is a plot of 66 acres which extends across two branches of Pitch and Tarr Swamp. It is bounded on the north by Mr James's Land and partly on the southwest by William Briscoes Orchard. Mr Sherwood's house and kitchen are identified in a one-acre plot on the western side of the area. Just outside this plot Mr. Chiles's house and Coll[?] White's house are indicated. Available: CW, LC
  - Clayton, John. [Jamestown]. 1688., 924
    Size: 6 x 22 cm. Oriented with southwest at the top. This sketch of the James River from Hogg Isld. to Sandy Bay is from the fourth page of John Clayton's letter to the Royal Society "giveing a farther Account of ye Soile & other observations of Virginia," dated August 17, 1688. James Town is shown on a peninsula with a narrow isthmus at Sandy Bay. The Back Creeke separates the northeastern side of the peninsula from the mainland. Archers Hope and Archers Hope Creek are indicated on the mainland. On the peninsula there is a semicircular fort near Sandy Bay and a square "old fort" much farther to the southeast. Five or six other structures form a row along the riverbank, and The Brick House is indicated on Back Creeke near the eastern end of the peninsula. The Swamp appears as a line running diagonally across the peninsula. In his letter Clayton suggests how to drain the swamp, describes how the isthmus floods in the spring tides forming "an absolute island," describes the two forts, and recommends Archers Hope Point as the best site for a fort. Available: CW, LC
  - Thornton, John, and Will Fisher. Virginia, Maryland, Pennsilvania, East & West New Jarsey. By John Thornton at ye Platt in the Minories And by Will: Fisher at ye Postorn Gate on Tower hill. London: [ca. 1690]., 925
    Size: 51 x 79.5 cm. Scale: 14 cm. = 15 English leagues Oriented with west at the top. Extends from the Atlantic coast to Charles City County and from Lower Norfolk County to Staten Island (36 & deg;30'N to 40 & deg;45'N). James T. is indicated but without sufficient precision to determine the land form. There appear to be three peninsulas and two islands in the vicinity of the label. Fremans Point, Queens Creek, City Creek, The Green Spring, and Kings Creek are indicated on the mainland. Available: CW, LC
  - A new Map of Virginia Mary-Land And the Improved Parts of Penn-sylvania and New-Jersey. London: Sold by Christopher Browne at the Globe near the west end of St. Pauls Church, [1695?], 926
    Size: 51 x 57 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 13 miles Extends from Cape Henry to New Jersey (36 & deg;55'N to 40 & deg;27'N) and from west of the fall line to the coast. Iames Town, Kings Creek, Queens Creek, Greenspring, and Freemans[?] Point are indicated. Available: CW, LC
  - A New Map of Virginia, Maryland, Pensilvania, New Jersey, Part of New York, and Carolina. London: Sold by Reeve Williams, Mathematician, at his House at the North West Corner of St. Michaels Ally, in Corn-hill. By John Thornton at the Signe of England, Scotland, and Ireland, in the Mino(?). And by Robt. Morden at the Atlas in Corn-hill. Printed by T. Ilive, 1698., 927
    Size: 104 x 113.5 cm. (including two columns of text) Scale: 11 cm. = 30 miles Extends from the upper Carolina coast to Long Island Sound (36 & deg;35'N to 41 & deg;20'N) and from west of the fall line to the coast. An inset shows the Outer Banks and Albemarle Sound area of Carolina. James Town, Kings Creek, Queens Creek, the Green Spring, and Freemans Point are indicated. A column of text on each side of the map consists of descriptions of the colonies. The lengthy description of Virginia deals with discovery and exploration, Indian relations, geography, government, economy, climate, and wildlife. Sir William Berkeley is referred to as "the present Governor." James-Town, "the principal Seat of the English," is described as being "situated in a Peninsula" and as having "many fair Houses, whereof some are of Brick." Available: CW, PRO
  - Michel, Francis Louis. [Virginia-Chesapeake Bay Area]. [1702]., 928
    Size: 26 x 34 cm. Oriented with west at the top. Extends from the coast to Charles City and from Cape Henry to the Potomac River. Jems Conti[?] is labeled, but the primitive sketch (from Michel's diary, 1701-1702) does not accurately indicate the shape of the land. Available: CW
  - Jeffreys, Simon. This is a plan of one hundred and two acres of Governors land lying and being in the maine in James City County. Surveyed for the Honble. Phillip Ludwell Esq. May the 27th 1712 pr Simon Jeffreys Surveyor J.C.C. 1712., 929
    Size: 41 x 34 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 8 single chains The land is bounded partly by the James River, a "small swamp," and the "main road from Jamestown." A road "up the country" crosses the property and meets the road from Jamestown where the latter becomes the road "to Williamsburg." Available: CW
  - Homann, Johann Baptist. Virginia Marylandia et Carolina in America Septentrionali Britannorum. Nuremberg: [1714]., 930
    Size: 49.5 x 58.5 cm. Scale: 7 cm. = ca. 20 Milliaria Germanica Extends from Cape Fear to Connecticut (33 & deg;N to 42 & deg;N) and from Lake Erie to the Atlantic coast. The coast, bays, and rivers are rather accurately charted, but places are not. James Towne is located on the mainland about halfway between the mouth of the Chickahominy River and the mouth of the James River. The Green (Greenspring?), Kiskiack, and Kecoughtan are also indicated. Published in Homann's Geographicus Major (1759-1784), II, #86. Available: CW, LC
  - A New Map of Virginia, Maryland, Pensilvania, New Jersey, Part of New York, and Carolina. Sold by T: Page W: & F Mount on Tower Hill, [ca. 1725-1728]., 931
    Size: 103 x 85.5 cm. Appears to be the same map as A New Map of Virginia... (ENTRY 927), but without the columns of text. The only other change noted, besides the names of the sellers, is in the dedication "to Mr. Micajah Perry of London Merchant." The 1698 version went on to state that the map is dedicated and presented by Williams, Thornton, and Morden. On this later version only the name Thornton remains. Available: CW, CLM
  - Moll, H. Virginia and Maryland. [1729]., 932
    Size: 27 x 20 cm. Scale: 4 cm. = ca. 29 English miles Extends from Cape Henry to Baltimore (37 & deg;N to 39 & deg;50'N) and from about the fall line to the Atlantic coast. The label for Iames To. is in the Iames River, but near a peninsula. Colledg, City Creek, and York County are also indicated. The label for Iames County is west of the Chicahomon River. Published in Moll's Atlas Minor (1736). Available: CW, LC
  - A General Map of the known and inhabited Parts of Virginia. [1731]., 933
    Size: 52 x 68 cm. Extends from below the Carolina border to the confluence of the Shenandoah and Potomac rivers (36 & deg;N to 39 & deg;55'N) and from the Blue Ridge to the Atlantic coast. James Town appears as a peninsula. Williamsburg, York, and the counties are indicated. Available: CW, PRO
  - Tiddeman, Mark. A Draught of Virginia from the Capes to York in York River and to Kuiquotan or Hamton in James River. London: Printed & sold by Page & Mount on Tower Hill, [1737]., 934
    Size: 45 x 58.5 cm. Scale: 19.5 cm. = 5 leagues = 15 miles Extends from Norfolk to Gloucester and from James City Isle to Eastern Shore. This is the first of two states identified by Verner. Each state appeared in several editions of The English Pilot: The Fourth Book from 1729 to 1794. The second state, which first appeared in 1751, contained no major cartographic changes; its imprint was "Sold by W. & I. Mount & T. Page on Tower Hill London." Reference: Coolie Verner, A Carto-Bibliographical Study of The English Pilot: The Fourth Book. Available: CW, LC
  - Bowen, Eman. A New and Accurate Map of Virginia & Maryland Laid Down from Surveys and Regulated by Astronl. Observatns. [1747]., 935
    Size: 32.5 x 23 cm. Scale: 1.6 cm. = 10 English miles Shows the full length of the Chesapeake Bay (36 & deg;50'N to 40 & deg;N) and from about the fall line to the coast (77 & deg;W to 74 & deg;5'W). James To. is shown on a peninsula. College Creek is also indicated. This map appeared in A Complete System of Geography (1747) and in Bowen's Complete Atlas (1752). Reference: Earl G. Swem, Maps Relating to Virginia, 61-62. Available: CW
  - Fry, Joshua, and Peter Jefferson. A Map of the Inhabited part of Virginia containing the whole Province of Maryland with Part of Pensilvania, New Jersey and North Carolina. Drawn by Joshua Fry & Peter Jefferson in 1751. London: Engrav'd and Publish'd according to Act of Parliament by Thos. Jefferys Geographer to his Royal Highness the Prince of Wales at the Corner of St. Martins Lane, Charing Cross, [1753-1754]., 936
    Size: 77 x 118 cm., divided into four plates each ca. 40 x 60 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 10.33 miles Extends from Albemarle Sound to Philadelphia (35 & deg;45'N to 40 & deg;12'N) and from the Alleghenies to the Atlantic coast (82 & deg;19'W to 74 & deg;W). James Town is shown on a peninsula. Also indicated are Green Spring, Powhatan Swamp, Williamsburg, and various plantations. Seven additional English states (1755-1794) and six French impressions have been identified. All subsequent English versions contain the word "most" in the title (A Map of the most Inhabited part of Virginia...) Also added were some roads and mileage tables by J. Dalrymple. Reference: The Fry and Jefferson Map of Virginia and Maryland: Facsimiles of the 1754 and 1794 Printings with an Index (Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1966). Available: CW
  - Bellin, Jacques Nicolas. Carte de la Virginie, Avec Partie du Maryland et de la Pensilvanie. Suivant ce que les Anglois en ont publi & eacute; de plus recent. Par le Sr. Bellin Ingenieur de la Marine. 1755., 937
    Size: 45 x 66 cm. Extends from Albemarle Sound to Philadelphia (36 & deg;N to 40 & deg;N) and from the New River to the Atlantic coast. James Town appears to be on a peninsula. Williamsburg is also indicated. Available: CW; Archives Marine, Paris
  - Kitchin, T. A New Map of Virginia, from the best Authorities. [1761]., 938
    Size: 18 x 23 cm. Scale: 3.7 cm. = 60 British statute miles Extends from Currituck Inlet to southern Pennsylvania (36 & deg;10'N to 40 & deg;N) and from the New River to Eastern Shore (82 & deg;25'W to 75 & deg;40'W). James T. and Williamsburg are indicated. Published in The London Magazine, November 1761. Available: CW
  - [Bellin, Jacques Nicolas]. Carte de la Virginie Mari-land & a. Tir & eacute;e des meilleures Cartes Angloises. [1764]., 939
    Size: 18.5 x 30 cm. Scale: 1 cm. = 5 Lieues Communes Extends from Cape Henry to Philadelphia (37 & deg;N to 40 & deg;N) and from western Maryland to the Atlantic coast. The James Town label is in the middle of the James River; the symbol for the place appears to be on the peninsula that forms the western side of the mouth of the Chickahominy River. Williamsburg is also indicated. The map was published in Bellin's Le petit atlas maritime (1764), vol. 1, no. 35. Available: CW, LC
  - [Salmon, Thomas]. A Map of Virginia and Maryland. [1767]., 940
    Size: 14.5 x 19.5 cm. Extends from Albemarle Sound to Philadelphia (36 & deg;N to 40 & deg;N) and from the Allagany Mountains to the Atlantic coast. James T. appears to be on a peninsula. Williamsburg is also indicated. The map was published opposite p. 569 in Salmon's A New Geographical and Historical Grammar (1767). Available: CW
  - Henry, John. A New and Accurate Map of Virginia Wherein most of the Counties are laid down from Actual Surveys. With A Concise Account of the Number of Inhabitants, the Trade, Soil, and Produce of that Province. Engraved by Thomas Jefferys Geographer to the King. London: Published according to Act of Parliament for the Author by Thos. Jefferys at the Corner of St. Martins Lane in the Strand, February 1770., 941
    Size: 97 x 131 cm. Scale: 5 7/16 in. = 40 British statute miles Extends from the Carolina line to Frederick County (ca. 36 & deg;30'N to 39 & deg;55'N) and from the New River to Eastern Shore. James Town is shown on the James River in James City County, with no indication of a peninsula or island. Green Spring, Williamsburg, Powhatan, and Archers Hope Creek are also indicated. Available: CW
  - Simiti & egrave;re, Pierre Eug & egrave;ne du. Map of the Maritime Parts of Virginia Exhibiting the Seat of War and of Ld. Dunmore's depredations in that Colony. P.E.D. Delint. R.A. Sculp. for the Pennsa. Mag. p. 184. [1775]., 942
    Size: 24 x 27 cm. Scale: 7 cm. = 30 miles Extends from Suffolk to St. Marys (Md.) and from James City County to the Atlantic coast. James Town is on a peninsula and is connected by road to Williamsburgh. Archershope is also indicated. The map was published in the Pennsylvania Magazine (April 1775): 184. Available: CW, Historical Society of Pennsylvania
  - Smith, Anthony. A New and Accurate Chart of the Bay of Chesapeake, with all the Shoals, Channels, Islands, Entrances, Soundings, and Sailing-marks, as far as the Navigable Part of the Rivers Patowmack, Patapsco and North-east. Drawn from Several Draughts made by the most Experienced Navigators, Chiefly from those of Anthony Smith Pilot of St. Marys; and compared with the Modern Surveys of Virginia and Maryland. London: Printed for Robert Sayer and John Bennett, Map & Chartsellers, at No. 53 in Fleet Street, as the Act directs, 1st. July 1776., 943
    Size: 96.5 x 142 cm. Oriented with west at the top. Extends from the Atlantic coast to Jamestown and from Suffolk to the northern end of Chesapeake Bay (36 & deg;40'N to 39 & deg;45'N). Navigation directions and observations are printed on the chart in various locations, including "Directions for Sailing into James River." James Town is on a peninsula. Powhatan, Archers Hope, and Williamsburg are also indicated. Available: CW, LC
  - ---. Carte de la Baie de Chesapeake et de la Partie navigable des Rivieres, James, York, Patowmack, Patuxen, Patapsco, North-East, Choptank et Pokomack. Redig & eacute;e pour le service des Vaisseaux du Roi, au D & eacute;p & ocirc;t G & eacute;n & eacute;ral des Cartes, Plans et Journaux de la Marine, Par Ordre de M. de Sartine, Conseiller d'Etat, Ministre et Secr & eacute;taire d'Etat au D & eacute;partment de la Marine, d'apr & egrave;s des Plans Anglois, et particulierement ceux d'Antoine Smith, Pilote de Ste. Marie. 1778., 944
    Size: 58.5 x 86 cm. This essentially is a French edition of the Anthony Smith map of 1776. It appeared as no. 22 in Neptune Americo-Septentrional, published by the D & eacute;p & ocirc;t des Cartes et Plans de la Marine (1778-1780). Available: CW, LC
  - Des Barres, Joseph Frederick Wallet. A Chart of the Coast of New York, New Jersey, Pensilvania, Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina & c. Composed from the Deposit of Surveys of the Right Honourable the Lords of Trade, with Soundings and Nautical Remarks from Lt. Jno. Knight of the Navy & others. [London]: Published According to Act of Parliament by J.F W. Des Barres, Esqr., March 1, 1780., 945
    Size: 158.5 x 74.5 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 10 statute miles Extends from 34 & deg;37'N to 41 & deg;32'N. James To. is on a peninsula. Williamsburg is also indicated. This map was published in Des Barres's The Atlantic Neptune. Reference: Earl G. Swem, Maps Relating to Virginia, 73. Available: CW, LC
  - [Berthier, Louis-Alexandre]. [Environs of Williamsburg and Yorktown]. [1781-1782]., 946
    Size: 68 x 83 cm. Unfinished map which extends from Point Comfort to Mobjack Bay and from Mill Creek to Chesapeake Bay. Detail is in the Williamsburg, Yorktown, and Gloucester Point areas only; other sections are faintly sketched, including what may be the eastern end of Jamestown Island. There are no place names, except for a few scribbled in the unfinished section. The detailed areas include watercourses, indications of buildings, and what may be military emplacements around Yorktown and Williamsburg and on the James River near College Creek. Reference: Howard C. Rice, Jr., and Anne S. K. Brown, The American Campaigns of Rochambeau's Army, 2: map 91. Available: CW; Soci & eacute;t & eacute; d'Encouragement & agrave; l'Elevage du Cheval Fran & ccedil;ais, Château de Grosbois, Boissy-Saint-Leger
  - Capitaine du Chesnoy, Michel. Carte de la Campagne en Virginie du Major G & eacute;n & eacute;ral Mis. de la Fayette ou se trouvent les Camps et marches ainsy que ceux du Lieutent. G & eacute;n & eacute;ral Lord Cornwallis en 1781. Par le Major Capitaine A.d.C. du Gl. la Fayette. 1781., 947
    Size: 93 x 148 cm., including text Scale: 11.1 cm. = 15 miles Extends from Goochland County to the Chesapeake Bay and from Portsmouth to Fredericksburg. Includes a column of text down the left side describing the movements and engagements of the British and American forces from April through the surrender in October. Lines of march and encampments are indicated on the map. James-Town is shown on a peninsula, though the text refers to "James Island." The lines representing troop movements indicate that British forces were at Jamestown on two occasions. Reference: Peter J. Guthorn, American Maps and Map Makers of the Revolution, 12. Available: CW, Yale University Library
  - Carte de la Campagne de la division aux ordres du Mis. de St. Simon en Virginie depuis le 2. 7bre. 1781 Jusqu-a la Reddition d'Yorck le 19. 8bre. m & ecirc;me ann & eacute;e. 1781., 948
    Size: 45 x 67 cm. Scale: 26.7 cm. = 6000 toises = ca. 7 miles Extends from Green Spring to Yorktown. Isle de James Town appears to be connected to the mainland by a bridge. Shows encampments at Jamestown and at Meen, which appears to be at about where the marina is currently located on Powhatan Creek. Also indicates a church on the road to Williamsburg just west of Powhatan Creek. Roads, cleared land, and buildings are indicated. Very similar in concept to the Pechon map. Reference: Coolie Verner, Maps of the Yorktown Campaign 1780-1781, 32. Available: CW
  - Chantavoine. Carte de la Virginie ou pr & eacute;cis de la Campagne de 1781., 949
    Size: 116 x 83 cm. James town appears to be on an island. Two lines, apparently indicating troop movement, pass through the town. Green Spring, Powhatan, Archers hope, and Williamsburg are indicated on the mainland. A column on the left side of the map contains text "pour servir & agrave; l'intelligence de la carte." Reference: Coolie Verner, Maps of the Yorktown Campaign 1780-1781, 32. Available: CW, LC
  - [Courses of the York and James Rivers]. [Ca. 1781]., 950
    Size: 75 x 117.5 cm. Oriented with northeast at the top. Extends from Suffolk to Mobjack Bay and from Varina (east of Richmond) to Cape Henry. Some labels are in French. James town is on a rather broad peninsula. Green Spring, Powhatan Creek, Williamsburg, and Archers Hope are indicated on the mainland. Reference: Coolie Verner, Maps of the Yorktown Campaign 1780-1781, 24. Available: CW, LC
  - [Crublier d'Opterre, Henri]. Virginie Embouchure de la Baye de Chesapeake a Environs de Williamburg, york, hampton, Et Portsmouth. [1781]., 951
    Size: 23.5 x 17.5 cm. (CW copy) Scale: 7.1 cm. = 20 miles Oriented with north-northwest at the top. Extends from Grand Marais (Dismal Swamp) to Williamburg and from the Jamestown area to Cape Charles. Jamestown is not labeled, but a peninsula is depicted. Williamburg, Kemps, Hayes, and Custiss Mill are indicated. Depicted but not labeled are what appear to be Powhatan Creek, Lake Powell, College Creek, Lake Matoaka, and Queen's Creek. Available: CW; Collection of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Va.
  - Desandro & uuml;ins. Plan du terrein & agrave; la Rive Gauche de la Riviere de James vis- & agrave;-vis James-Town en Virginie ou s'est livr & eacute; le Combat du 6 juillet 1781 entre l'arm & eacute;e am & eacute;ricaine command & eacute;e par le Mis. de la Fayette et l'arm & eacute;e angloise aux ordres du Lord Cornwallis. 1781., 952
    Size: 45 x 46 cm. Scale: 9.5 cm. = 800 toises = ca. 1 mile Extends from the western end of the island where Jamestown is located to Green Spring. A ferry is shown connecting the island to the mainland. Roads, wooded areas, and buildings are indicated, as are military positions, which are centered around Mr. Harris's property about halfway between the island and Green Spring. Neck Land's, Humbler's plantation, and a church on the road to Williamsburg are also indicated. The title, a legend, and the scale occupy the left side of the sheet (13.5 cm.) Available: CW, LC
  - Hills, John. Plan of the Peninsula of Chesopeak Bay. Compiled from actual Surveys By Iohn Hills Assistant Engineer. 1781., 953
    Size: 71 x 124 cm. Scale: 1 in. = 5 miles Oriented with west at the top. Extends from the Eastern Shore to James Town and from Norfolk to Philadelphia. James Town is shown at the eastern end of a peninsula. Williamsburg and Archers Hope are also indicated. References: Coolie Verner, Maps of the Yorktown Campaign 1780-1781, 21; Peter J. Guthorn, British Maps of the American Revolution, 24. Available: CW, CLM
  - Pechon. Carte de la Campagne faite en Virginie en 1781. Lev & eacute; en sepbre. et octbre. par Pechon, aide de camps de Mr. le Mis. de St. Simon. 1781., 954
    Size: 28 x 56 cm. Scale: 1 in. = ca. 1.2 miles Extends from Green Spring to Yorktown. It is unclear whether James-Town is on an island or if there is an isthmus. Roads and cleared land are shown, as well as troop positions. Some individual structures might be discernible on a full-sized copy. Reference: Coolie Verner, Maps of the Yorktown Campaign 1780-1781, 32. Available: CW
  - Plan des Environs de Williamsburg, York, Hampton et Portsmouth. [1781?], 955
    Size: 30.5 x 27.5 cm. Scale: 10.7 cm. = 20 miles Extends from Dismal Swamp to Gloucester and from Jamestown to Cape Henry. Jamestown is not labeled but appears as a peninsula. Roads are indicated, though none extend onto the Jamestown peninsula. Available: CW, LC
  - A Plan of the Entrance of Chesapeak Bay, with James and York Rivers; wherein are shewn the Respective Positions (in the beginning of October) 1. of the British Army Commanded by Lord Cornwallis, at Gloucester and York in Virginia; 2. of the American and French Forces under General Washington, 3. and of the French Fleet under Count de Grasse. By an Officer. London: Published by Wm. Faden Charing Cross, Novr. 26th 1781., 956
    Size: 43 x 53.5 cm. Scale: 6.5 cm. = 10 miles Extends from Suffolk to the mouth of the Rappahannock River and from Jamestown to the coast. Jamestown is shown on a peninsula. A road is indicated from Williamsburg, and a dotted line from Jamestown across the river to Cobham perhaps represents a ferry. Powhatan Creek and Archers Hope are indicated. Available: CW, CLM
  - Desandro & uuml;ins. Carte des Environs de Williamsburg en Virginie o & ugrave; les Arm & eacute;es Fran & ccedil;oise et Am & eacute;ricaine ont Camp & eacute;s en Septembre 1781. Arm & eacute;e de Rochambeau, 1782., 957